<!-- $Id: introduction.xml,v 1.2 2004/08/05 14:00:34 danieldk Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>
<title>An introduction to Libranet GNU/Linux</title>

<sect1>
<title>What is Linux?</title>

<para>
Linux is a Unix-like kernel which is written by Linus Torvalds
and other developers, who communicate using the Internet. Linux
runs on many different architectures, for example on many IA32, IA64,
AMD64, Alpha, m68k, SPARC and PowerPC machines. The latest kernel and
more information can be found at:
<ulink url="http://www.kernel.org">http://www.kernel.org</ulink>
</para>

<para>
Linux is often confused with the GNU/Linux system. Linux is only a
kernel, not a complete operating system. GNU/Linux consists of the
GNU operating system with the Linux kernel. Please read the following
section for a more detailed explanation of GNU/Linux.
</para>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>What is GNU/Linux?</title>

<para>
At the beginning of the eighties Richard Stallman started an ambitious
project with the goal to write a free Unix-like operating system. The
name of this system is GNU (GNU is Not Unix). At the beginning of the
nineties most important components of the GNU operating system were
written, except for the kernel, which is still under development under
the name HURD. HURD consists of some servers which provide Unix-like
kernel functionality. In turn these servers run under the Mach micro-kernel.
At the beginning at the nineties the HURD team still had to wait till
the Mach sources were released as free software. In the meanwhile Linus
started filling the gap with the Linux kernel. GNU/Linux thus refers
to the GNU system running on the Linux kernel. Right now the HURD
kernel is also in a usable state and can be downloaded in the form
of the GNU/HURD operating system. The
<ulink url="http://www.debian.org/">Debian</ulink> project has even
developed a version of the GNU operating system which works with the
<ulink url="http://www.netbsd.org/">NetBSD</ulink> kernel. We should
call "Linux distributions" "GNU/Linux distributions", because GNU
is a substantial part of most distributions. 
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>What is Libranet GNU/Linux?</title>

<para>
Libranet is a GNU/Linux distribution that is based on Debian GNU/Linux.
Debian provides a huge package collection and an excellent package
management tool named APT. Libranet builds on the reliable Debian base
and adds an excellent installation program and a configuration tool
named AdminMenu. Besides that Libranet includes a carefully selected
collection of software. Distinguishing features that are often mentioned
are:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
A user friendly installer.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
The AdminMenu configuration tool.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
A wide selection of packages.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Good support.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
A friendly and helpful community.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Getting Libranet GNU/Linux</title>
<para>
Libranet can be purchased on the Libranet site as a download, or on
CD-ROM. Besides that there are many software and Linux vendors around the
world that provide Libranet on CD-ROM. The official Libranet site can
be found at 
<ulink url="http://www.libranet.com/">http://www.libranet.com/</ulink>
</para>

<para>
Besides offering the latest Libranet version on CD-ROM or as a paid
download, Libranet Computer Systems Ltd. also offers an older downloadable
version for evaluating Libranet. Have a look at the Libranet site for
more information.
</para>
</sect1>

</chapter>
