<!-- $Id: netconfig.xml,v 1.4 2004/08/10 07:50:38 danieldk Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="netconfig.html"?>
<title>Network configuration</title>

<sect1>
<title>Adminmenu</title>

<sect2>
<title>Setting up ethernet cards</title>

<para>
Ethernet cards can be configured by selecting <quote>expert</quote> and
then <quote>eth</quote> in the network configuration. The resulting screen
(<xref linkend="adminmenu-ethconfig" />) provides several options:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>modules</emphasis>: This option is used to load modules (drivers)
for the network adapters that you want to use.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>edit</emphasis>: You can configure the settings for an network
interface, like the IP address, and default route with this option.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>remove</emphasis>: The <emphasis>remove</emphasis> option
is used to remove the configuration for an interface.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<figure id="adminmenu-ethconfig">
<title>Ethernet configuration menu</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-ethconfig.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Interfaces are named in Linux, example names are <emphasis>eth2</emphasis>,
<emphasis>lo</emphasis> and <emphasis>ppp0</emphasis>. Normal (ethernet)
network interfaces are named <emphasis>ethn</emphasis>, in which 
<emphasis>n</emphasis> is a number starting with 0. For example, the first
network card is named <emphasis>eth0</emphasis>, the second
<emphasis>eth1</emphasis>, etc.
</para>

<sect3><title>Editing an interface</title>

<para>
You can configure an interface by selecting the <emphasis>edit</emphasis>
menu option described above. The next dialog will ask you which interface
you would like to configure (<xref linkend="adminmenu-intselect" />. Select
the interface you would like to configure to proceed.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-intselect">
<title>Selecting an interface to configure</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-intselect.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The first step of the configuration of an interface is choosing whether
you want to use a dynamic IP address or not. If you want to use a DHCP
server on the network, select <emphasis>dynamic</emphasis>. The rest
of this section is based on choosing <emphasis>static</emphasis>, because
using a dynamic IP address does not require further configuration except
for setting an optional hostname.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-intdhcp">
<title>Using a dynamic or static IP address</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-intdhcp.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
After choosing to use a static IP you can set the IP address of the
interface. If you have a home network you can safely use the
<emphasis>192.168.1.xxx</emphasis> range (where xxx is a number from
1 to 254). Please be aware that hosts on the same network should use
the same IP range. If you are going to use Libranet in a company
or institutional network, and you are not sure what IP address you
should use, ask the network administrator.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-intaddr">
<title>Setting the interface IP address</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-intaddr.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The next step is to set the netmask that should be used. On most smaller
networks this can be set to <emphasis>255.255.255.0</emphasis>, for
instance when all hosts are in the <emphasis>192.168.1.xxx</emphasis>
range. Ask your network administrator if you are not sure about what
netmask you should use.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-intnetmask">
<title>Setting the interface netmask</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-intnetmask.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Adminmenu will also ask you to enter the broadcast address, aside from
special situations you can leave this field blank. Linux will try to
determine the broadcast address automatically.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-intbroadcast">
<title>Setting the broadcast address</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-intbroadcast.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Finally you can set the default gateway. This is a host on the network
that routes traffic to other networks, for example the internet. This
is often called the default route. If you are using Libranet on a network
that is not connected to any other networks or the internet, you can
leave this setting blank.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-gateway">
<title>Setting the default gateway</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-gateway.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
At this point all settings for the interface are completed. Adminmenu
will ask you for a final confirmation on the selected values.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-intconfirm">
<title>Selecting an interface to configure</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-intconfirm.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring DNS</title>

<para>
DNS servers have a very special task in networking. They translate hostnames
(for instance www.libranet.com) to IP addresses. To be able to use hostnames
the system needs access to one or more DNS servers. Almost all Internet
service providers provide DNS servers. DNS can be configured by selecting
<quote>expert</quote> and then <quote>nameserver</quote> in the adminmenu
network configuration. Adminmenu will then ask for the nameservers
(<xref linkend="adminmenu-dns" />). You can enter the IP addresses in the
input field, separating them with a space.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-dns">
<title>Configuring DNS</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-dns.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Manual configuration</title>

<para>
This chapter explains how some common network-related configuration files
work. Most things can be configured with adminmenu, but more experienced
users might prefer configuring things by editing the relevant configuration
files.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring nameservers</title>

<para>
The name resolver is configured using the <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>
file. Nameservers that should be used can be configured by adding a lines of
the following form: <emphasis>nameserver &lt;IP address&gt;</emphasis>. For
example:
</para>

<screen>
nameserver 192.168.1.200
nameserver 192.168.1.201
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Local hosts</title>

<para>
Besides resolving using name servers specified in 
<filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>, GNU/Linux can also resolve hosts
that are specified in <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>. This file
is handy for adding names to local hosts, without the hassle of
configuring a local name server. Hosts are specified in the following
form: <emphasis>&lt;IP address&gt; &lt;name1&gt; ... &lt;namen&gt;</emphasis>.
This is an example of the <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file:
</para>

<screen>
127.0.0.1       localhost localhost.localdomain
192.168.1.1     host1.example.net
192.168.1.2	host2.example.net
</screen>

<para>
Be sure that there is an entry for the host name that is used (you can
display the host name with the <command>hostname</command> command). If the
host name is not resolvable some programs refuse to work correctly.
</para>

<note>
<para>
If you want to use the same <filename>hosts</filename> file on a relatively
large number of machines, it might we worth looking at the
<emphasis>dnsmasq</emphasis> package. Dnsmasq can provide a
<filename>hosts</filename> file on one host to a complete network through its 
DNS server.
</para>
</note>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
