<!-- $Id: internet.xml,v 1.2 2004/07/19 22:28:58 danieldk Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="internet.html"?>
<title>Using the Internet with Libranet</title>

<sect1>
<title>Browsing the web with Mozilla</title>

<para>
Mozilla is one of the most popular GNU/Linux browsers, and is rapidly gaining 
market share on the Windows platform. Many browsers are based on the Mozilla
rendering engine (named Gecko), for example FireFox, Epiphany and Galeon.
Mozilla is a complete suite, containing a web browser, an e-mail program,
a USENET client and a IRC client. This section is a short introduction to
Mozilla, and provides some hints that might be helpful.
</para>

<para>
Libranet includes Mozilla, and it can be installed via the conventional
Libranet package management tools. Mozilla can be started by launching
<quote>Apps/Net/Mozilla Navigator</quote>. The default Libranet graphical
environment also includes a Mozilla launcher in the main menu.
</para>

<figure id="mozilla-browser">
<title>The Mozilla browser</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/mozilla-browser.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<sect2>
<title>Plugins</title>

<para>
Some sites require plugins like Flash or Java. Realplayer, Flash, Java
and the MozPlugger plugins can be installed via AdminMenu. These options
are available under the <quote>Browser Plugins</quote> tab in AdminMenu.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Tabs</title>

<para>
Mozilla provides tabs, which means you do not have to open a new window
if you want to visit several sites simultaneously. You can just create
multiple tabs within one channel, which have different active sites.
Try pressing the &lt;Ctrl&gt; + &lt;t&gt; keys, as you can see a new
tab is opened in which you can start browsing. You can browse through
the tags with the &lt;Ctrl&gt; + &lt;Page Up&gt; and &lt;Ctrl&gt; + 
&lt;Page Down&gt; keys. You can also open a link in a new tab by
clicking on the link with the right mouse button and selecting
<quote>Open Link in New Tab</quote>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Popup blocking</title>

<para>
Many Internet sites display popup ads, which can become a bit annoying,
fortunately Mozilla has a function that blocks popup windows. This option
can be found in the preferences window, which is accessible from the
<quote>Edit</quote> menu. The popup window settings are located under
the <quote>Privacy & Security</quote> section.
</para>

<para>
Check the <quote>Block unrequested popup windows</quote> to block popup
Windows by default. There might be some sites that you regularly visit,
which have popup windows which you do not want to block. For these sites
an exception can be made by clicking the <quote>Allowed Sites</quote>
button. A new window will appear, which allows you to add sites that
should be excluded from the popup killer.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Ximian Evolution, the ultimate e-mail client</title>

<para>
Ximian Evolution is an e-mail client that offers alot of personal information
management (PIM) features, that is being developed by Novell. It features:
</para>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>
A summary page that can display the weather, newsfeeds, appointments,
tasks and other information, a calendar, an addressbook and much more.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
A calendar, which can be used for appointments and other stuff.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
An addressbook, which allows detailed configuration of contacts.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
PGP/GnuPG, SASL and SSL/TSL message encryption and/or signing.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Support for LDAP directory servers.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Much more.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<figure id="evolution">
<title>Ximian Evolution</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/evolution.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<sect2>
<title>The summary screen</title>

<para>
Evolution has a very nice summary screen, which can display the local
weather, news feeds appointments and tasks. This screen is easily
customizable. We will have a look at some options in this section.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>My weather</title>

<para>
The <quote>My Weather</quote> functionality allows you to display
information about the weather at one or more locations. To change
the weather options, open up the settings dialog by clicking on the
<quote>Tools -> Settings...</quote> menu item. Go to the
<quote>Summary Preferences</quote>, and click on the <quote>Weather</quote>
tab. The first list on the left shows all available locations for which
weather information can be shown. The right list shows which for which
locations weather is currently shown. You can add and remove locations
using the <quote>Add</quote> and <quote>Remove</quote> buttons. After
you have customized the <quote>Shown</quote> list you can choose to
show the weather in Celsius instead of Fahrenheit, by activating the
<quote>Celsius</quote> option. Click <quote>OK</quote> when you are
finished, and the <quote>My weather</quote> overview will show the weather
at the locations you selected.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>News feeds</title>

<para>
Evolution accepts news feeds in RSS or RDF formats. This is a standard for
supplying news feeds, and many news sites provide a RSS or RDF news feed.
The selection of news feeds can be customized in the settings dialog.
Click on the <quote>Tools -> Settings...</quote> menu item to open the
setting dialog. Select on the <quote>Summary Preferences</quote> icon,
and click the <quote>News Feeds</quote> tab to open the news feeds tab.
This tab works like the weather tab; a list of news feeds is listed
on the left side, the right list shows which news feeds are currently
displayed. You can remove or add items with the <quote>Add</quote>
and <quote>Remove</quote> buttons. It is also possible to add an unlisted
news feed, by clicking the <quote>New Feed</quote> button. Evolution will
ask you to input the name of the news feed, and the URL where the RDF/RSS
news feed can be found. Suppose that you would like to add the
<ulink url="http://www.osnews.com/">OSNews</ulink> news feed, you could
enter <emphasis>http://www.osnews.com/files/recent.rdf</emphasis> as the
URL.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Setting up e-mail accounts</title>

<para>
The next thing you will probably want to do is to setup some e-mail accounts.
The first time Evolution is started it will ask the user to setup an account,
so there is a good change that you have already set up an e-mail account.
The account settings are located under the <quote>Mail Accounts</quote>
icon in the Evolution settings dialog, which can be launched by clicking
the <quote>Tools -> Settings...</quote> menu item. In the account summary
you can add, edit and remove accounts.
</para>

<para>
Click the <quote>Add</quote> button to add an e-mail account. This will
launch an assistant that will help you setting up an account. Just
click <quote>Forward</quote> at the welcome screen. The assistant will
ask you for information about your identity. Here you can fill in the
name and e-mail address that will displayed in the <quote>From</quote> 
headers. If the address that users should apply to differs from the
e-mail address, fill in the optional <quote>Reply-To</quote> field.
If the reply address is identical to the e-mail address, this
field can be ignored. Optionally you can fill in the 
<quote>Organization</quote> field. Press <quote>Forward</quote> after
completing this form.
</para>

<para>
After setting the identity you can specify which mail server should
be used for sending mail. The <quote>None</quote> option is useful
if you just want to add an additional identity, but no other full
blown e-mail account. Suppose that you have two e-mail addresses,
<emphasis>sales@mycompany.com</emphasis> and 
<emphasis>ceo@mycompany.com</emphasis>, and e-mails to both addresses
are delivered to the same account. In this case you could set up
an extra identity, which will allow you to choose the 
appropriate <quote>From</quote> address. If you would like to receive
e-mail using this account, there are several server types you can
choose from. The most commonly used types are POP and IMAP. This
information should be supplied when you registered your e-mail
account. It is safe to test which works if you do not know which
type of server is used. After selecting the IMAP or POP server
types you can enter the name of the host or IP address of the
e-mail server, and the user name for the account. If you would like
to store the password for this account after the first time
you entered it, check the <quote>Remember this password</quote>
check-box. Clock <quote>Forward</quote> when you are finished.
The assistant will then ask you to tune the settings a bit, for
example, you can set your account up to check for new mail automatically.
Click <quote>Forward</quote> to go to the <quote>Sending E-Mail</quote>
configuration.
</para>

<para>
In the <quote>Sending E-Mail</quote> screen you can set up how
Evolution can send mail. Unless you have set up a local mail server
on the machine Evolution is worked on you should select <quote>SMTP</quote>
as the server type. You should also fill in the name or IP address of
the SMTP server. If your SMTP server requires authentication you
can check the <quote>Server requires authentication</quote> check-box,
and fill in the user name. Click <quote>Forward</quote> to continue.
</para>

<para>
The final setup screen will ask you to supply the name of this e-mail
account. You can fill in anything you like. Check the <quote>Make
this my default account</quote> check-box if you would like to make
this the default account. This means this account will be used by
default when you compose a new e-mail. After clicking <quote>Forward</quote>
the assistant will congratulate you with finishing the account configuration.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>GAIM, the universal instant messenger</title>

<para>
GAIM is one of those killer applications. Once you got used to it changes are
you never want to look back at other messengers. GAIM supports AIM, ICQ,
MSN Messenger, Yahoo, IRC, Jabber, Gadu-Gadu and Zephyr. The nice thing
about GAIM is that you can use these services simultaneously.
</para>


<figure id="gaim">
<title>The GAIM messenger</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/gaim.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<sect2>
<title>Some first advice</title>

<para>
There have been many problems in the past with supporting all messengers,
because many messaging protocols are closed. The Jabber protocol is a
big exception; it is an open protocol that is an official standard. The
Jabber user-base is quite large and surpassed ICQ in user numbers. There
are many Jabber clients available, for most commonly used platforms. Try
to convince yourself and friends to switch to Jabber. More information
about Jabber can be found at: <ulink url="http://www.jabber.org/" /> 
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring accounts</title>

<para>
When you launch GAIM for the first time you can setup accounts using
the accounts button. After you have installed GAIM you can setup accounts
with the <emphasis>Tools -> Accounts</emphasis> menu item. This will present
a window with the accounts that are currently configured. You can use
the <emphasis>Online</emphasis> check-box next to an account name to go 
online or off-line. If the <emphasis>Auto-login</emphasis> check-box is
checked GAIM will automatically log in the next time GAIM is launched.
Adding, modifying or deleting accounts is easy with the buttons on
the bottom side of the window. Adding an account should be fairly
straightforward, make sure you select the right protocol.
</para>

<para>
If GAIM does not work (well) with a supported protocol, you should
probably update your GAIM version. It often happens that the protocols
are changed slightly, which breaks third party clients like GAIM.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>
