<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="internet.html"?>
<title>Using the Internet with Libranet</title>

<sect1>
<title>Browsing the web with Mozilla</title>

<para>
Mozilla Firefox is one of the most popular GNU/Linux browsers, and is rapidly 
gaining market share on the Windows platform. Many browsers are based on the
same rendering engine that Firefox uses(Gecko), for example Epiphany and
Galeon. This section is a short introduction to Mozilla Firefox, and provides
some hints that might be helpful.
</para>

<para>
Libranet includes Firefox, and it can be installed via the conventional
Libranet package management tools. Firefox can be started by launching
<quote>Apps/Net/Mozilla Firefox</quote>. The default Libranet graphical
environment also includes a Firefox launcher in the main menu.
</para>

<figure id="mozilla-browser">
<title>The Mozilla Firefox browser</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/firefox.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<sect2>
<title>Plugins</title>

<para>
Some sites require plugins like Flash or Java. Realplayer, Flash, Java
and the MozPlugger plugins can be installed via from the Libranet archive
or CDs as the following packages:
<literallayout>
realplayer
macromedia-flashplayer
sun-j2re1.5
mozplugger
</literallayout>
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Tabs</title>

<figure id="mozilla-firefox-tabs">
<title>Mozilla Firefox browser tabs</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/firefox-tabs.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Firefox provides tabs, which means you do not have to open a new window
if you want to visit several sites simultaneously. You can just create
multiple tabs within one window, which have different active sites.
Try pressing the &lt;Ctrl&gt; + &lt;t&gt; keys, as you can see a new
tab is opened in which you can start browsing. You can browse through
the tags with the &lt;Ctrl&gt; + &lt;Page Up&gt; and &lt;Ctrl&gt; + 
&lt;Page Down&gt; keys. You can also open a link in a new tab by
clicking on the link with the right mouse button and selecting
<quote>Open Link in New Tab</quote>.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Popup blocking</title>

<para>
Many Internet sites display popup ads, which can become a bit annoying,
fortunately Firefox has a function that blocks popup windows. This option
can be found in the preferences window, which is accessible from the
<quote>Edit</quote> menu. The popup window settings are located under
the <quote>Web features</quote> section. By default the <emphasis>Block
Popup Windows</emphasis> option is enabled. You can allow popups for
specific sites after clicking the <emphasis>Allowed sites</emphasis>
button.
</para>

</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Mozilla Thunderbird</title>

<para>
Mozilla Thunderbird is the e-mail client that is developed by the Mozilla
project. Together with Firefox, Thunderbird offers an excellent Internet
application suite. Thunderbird features:
</para>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>
An intelligent, integrated spam filter.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
A built-in RSS newsfeed reader.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
An addressbook with LDAP support, which allows detailed configuration
of contacts.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
Support for SSL/TSL message encryption and/or signing, and support
of GnuPG through the Enigmail extension.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
An extension architecture that will let you expand the functionality
of Thunderbird easily.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<figure id="thunderbird">
<title>Mozilla Thunderbird</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/applications/internet/thunderbird.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<sect2>
<title>Setting up e-mail accounts</title>

<para>
The next thing you will probably want to do is to setup some E-Mail accounts.
The first time Thunderbird is started it will ask the user to setup an account,
so there is a good change that you have already set up an E-Mail account. The
account settings window is available available through the <emphasis>Edit ->
Properties</emphasis> menu item. In the account settings window you can add,
edit and remove accounts.
</para>

<para>
Click the "Add Account" button to add an e-mail account. This will launch
an assistant that will help you setting up an account. Thunderbird will
first ask you what kind of account you would like to set up. Select
<emphasis>Email account</emphasis>, and click on the <emphasis>Next</emphasis>
button.
</para>

<para>
The first step of setting up an e-mail account is filling in some identity
information. You can fill your name in the <emphasis>Your Name</emphasis>
input field, and the E-Mail address that is used for this account in the
<emphasis>Email Address</emphasis> field.
</para>

<para>
The next step is to choose what kind of E-Mail server you will be using.
Most provides provide both POP and IMAP access to e-mail accounts. POP
is an older protocol that downloads all messages from the e-mail server.
IMAP leaves the messages on the server, and downloads the messages
when that is demanded (e.g. when a message is selected from the message
list). But in any case IMAP will keep the messages on the server. If
you have a dial-up connection, it is usually best to use POP to avoid having
to stay online to read e-mail, if you read e-mail from many different
locations IMAP is the obvious protocol choice. With both protocols you
will have to fill in the name of the e-mail server in the <emphasis>Incoming
Server</emphasis> input field. After you have chosen a protocol and filled
in the server name, you can click on <emphasis>Next</emphasis> to continue
the configuration. The next step is still closely related to the previous
step - Thunderbird will ask you to fill in the user name for the incoming
server. Fill in this user name in the <emphasis>Incoming User Name</emphasis>
field, and click the <emphasis>Next</emphasis> button.
</para>

<para>
Finally, Thunderbird will ask you to give a name for the account you have
just set up. You can fill in this name, and click on <emphasis>Next</emphasis>
to finish the configuration. Thunderbird will show the account settings
you have just made. You can confirm these settings with the
<emphasis>Finish</emphasis> button.
</para>

<para>
If this is the first account that you are setting up, Thunderbird will also
ask you to specify a server and username for outgoing mail. This is the SMTP
server that is provided by your ISP or E-Mail provider.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>GAIM, the universal instant messenger</title>

<para>
GAIM is one of those killer applications. Once you got used to it changes are
you never want to look back at other messengers. GAIM supports AIM, ICQ,
MSN Messenger, Yahoo, IRC, Jabber, Gadu-Gadu and Zephyr. The nice thing
about GAIM is that you can use these services simultaneously.
</para>


<figure id="gaim">
<title>The GAIM messenger</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/gaim.jpg" format="JPG" scale="60" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<sect2>
<title>Some first advice</title>

<para>
There have been many problems in the past with supporting all messengers,
because many messaging protocols are closed. The Jabber protocol is a
big exception; it is an open protocol that is an official standard. The
Jabber user-base is quite large and surpassed ICQ in user numbers. There
are many Jabber clients available, for most commonly used platforms. Try
to convince yourself and friends to switch to Jabber. More information
about Jabber can be found at: <ulink url="http://www.jabber.org/" /> 
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring accounts</title>

<para>
When you launch GAIM for the first time you can setup accounts using
the accounts button. After you have installed GAIM you can setup accounts
with the <emphasis>Tools -> Accounts</emphasis> menu item. This will present
a window with the accounts that are currently configured. You can use
the <emphasis>Online</emphasis> check-box next to an account name to go 
online or off-line. If the <emphasis>Auto-login</emphasis> check-box is
checked GAIM will automatically log in the next time GAIM is launched.
Adding, modifying or deleting accounts is easy with the buttons on
the bottom side of the window. Adding an account should be fairly
straightforward, make sure you select the right protocol.
</para>

<para>
If GAIM does not work (well) with a supported protocol, you should
probably update your GAIM version. It often happens that the protocols
are changed slightly, which breaks third party clients like GAIM.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>
