<!-- $Id: netconfig.xml,v 1.4 2004/08/10 07:50:38 danieldk Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="netconfig.html"?>
<title>Network configuration</title>

<sect1>
<title>Adminmenu</title>

<sect2>
<title>Setting up ethernet cards</title>

<para>
Ethernet cards can be configured with the <emphasis>Edit network
configuration</emphasis> item that is available through the
<emphasis>Network &amp; Internet</emphasis> tab in Adminmenu.
</para>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring DNS</title>

<para>
DNS servers have a very special task in networking. They translate hostnames
(for instance www.libranet.com) to IP addresses. To be able to use hostnames
the system needs access to one or more DNS servers. Almost all Internet
service providers provide DNS servers. DNS can be configured per interface
via the <emphasis>Network configuration</emphasis> item in Adminmenu.
To change the DNS server for an interface, select the network connection,
and click on <emphasis>Edit connection properties</emphasis>. The DNS
settings are then available under the <emphasis>DNS</emphasis> tab
(<xref linkend="adminmenu-dns" />). You can add a DNS server with the
<emphasis>Add</emphasis> button, or remove the selected server with the
<emphasis>Delete</emphasis> button.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-dns">
<title>Configuring DNS</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-dns.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Manual configuration</title>

<para>
This chapter explains how some common network-related configuration files
work. Most things can be configured with adminmenu, but more experienced
users might prefer configuring things by editing the relevant configuration
files.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring nameservers</title>

<para>
The name resolver is configured using the <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>
file. This file is dynamically generated, based on the interface settings.
You manually add entries by editing
<filename>/etc/resolvconf/resolv.conf.d/base</filename> Nameservers that should be used can be configured by adding a lines of
the following form: <emphasis>nameserver &lt;IP address&gt;</emphasis>. For
example:
</para>

<screen>
nameserver 192.168.1.200
nameserver 192.168.1.201
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Local hosts</title>

<para>
Besides resolving using name servers specified in 
<filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>, GNU/Linux can also resolve hosts
that are specified in <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>. This file
is handy for adding names to local hosts, without the hassle of
configuring a local name server. Hosts are specified in the following
form: <emphasis>&lt;IP address&gt; &lt;name1&gt; ... &lt;namen&gt;</emphasis>.
This is an example of the <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file:
</para>

<screen>
127.0.0.1       localhost localhost.localdomain
192.168.1.1     host1.example.net
192.168.1.2	host2.example.net
</screen>

<para>
Be sure that there is an entry for the host name that is used (you can
display the host name with the <command>hostname</command> command). If the
host name is not resolvable some programs refuse to work correctly.
</para>

<note>
<para>
If you want to use the same <filename>hosts</filename> file on a relatively
large number of machines, it might we worth looking at the
<emphasis>dnsmasq</emphasis> package. Dnsmasq can provide a
<filename>hosts</filename> file on one host to a complete network through its 
DNS server.
</para>
</note>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
