<!-- $Id: netconfig.xml,v 1.3 2004/08/02 11:43:34 danieldk Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="netconfig.html"?>
<title>Network configuration</title>

<sect1>
<title>Adminmenu</title>

<sect2>
<title>Setting up ethernet cards</title>

<para>
Ethernet cards can be configured by selecting <quote>expert</quote> and
then <quote>eth</quote> in the network configuration. The resulting screen
(<xref linkend="adminmenu-ethconfig" />) provides several options:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>modules</emphasis>: This option is used to load modules (drivers)
for the network adapters that you want to use.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>edit</emphasis>: You can configure the settings for an network
interface, like the IP address, and default route with this option.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>remove</emphasis>: The <emphasis>remove</emphasis> option
is used to remove the configuration for an interface.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<figure id="adminmenu-ethconfig">
<title>Ethernet configuration menu</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-ethconfig.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
Interfaces are named in Linux, example names are <emphasis>eth2</emphasis>,
<emphasis>lo</emphasis> and <emphasis>ppp0</emphasis>. Normal (ethernet)
network interfaces are named <emphasis>ethn</emphasis>, in which 
<emphasis>n</emphasis> is a number starting with 0. For example, the first
network card is named <emphasis>eth0</emphasis>, the second
<emphasis>eth1</emphasis>, etc.
</para>

<sect3><title>Editing an interface</title>

<para>
You can configure an interface by selecting the <emphasis>edit</emphasis>
menu option described above. The next dialog will ask you which interface
you would like to configure (<xref linkend="adminmenu-intselect" />. Select
the interface you would like to configure to proceed.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-intselect">
<title>Selecting an interface to configure</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-intselect.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

</sect3>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring DNS</title>

<para>
DNS servers have a very special task in networking. They translate hostnames
(for instance www.libranet.com) to IP addresses. To be able to use hostnames
the system needs access to one or more DNS servers. Almost all Internet
service providers provide DNS servers. DNS can be configured by selecting
<quote>expert</quote> and then <quote>nameserver</quote> in the adminmenu
network configuration. Adminmenu will then ask for the nameservers
(<xref linkend="adminmenu-dns" />). You can enter the IP addresses in the
input field, separating them with a space.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-dns">
<title>Configuring DNS</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu-dns.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Manual configuration</title>

<para>
This chapter explains how some common network-related configuration files
work. Most things can be configured with adminmenu, but more experienced
users might prefer configuring things by editing the relevant configuration
files.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring DNS</title>

<para>
The name resolver is configured using the <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>
file. Nameservers that should be used can be configured by adding a lines of
the following form: <emphasis>nameserver &lt;IP address&gt;</emphasis>. For
example:
</para>

<screen>
nameserver 192.168.1.200
nameserver 192.168.1.201
</screen>
</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
