<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="netconfig.html"?>
<title>Network configuration</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Most aspect of the Libranet network configuration can be configured through
the <emphasis>Network &amp; Internet</emphasis> tab in Adminmenu.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-network">
<title>The <emphasis>Network &amp; Internet</emphasis> page button</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/pagebutton.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The <emphasis>Network &amp; Internet</emphasis> page contains these items:

<itemizedlist>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Edit network configuration</emphasis>: This item is
      used to configure various kinds of network interfaces, for example
      LAN, DSL, Cable, PPPoE, Wireless and dial-up connections.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Network configuration wizard</emphasis>: This item
      will try to configure network interfaces automatically.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Set hostname</emphasis>: With this item you can
      set the system hostname.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Configure firewall</emphasis>: With this item you
      can configure the Libranet firewall. A firewall is used to
      block connections from or to a system that are not authorized,
      and internet connection sharing (NAT) can be switched on
      in the firewall configuration.
    </para>
  </listitem>
  <listitem>
    <para>
      <emphasis>Configure NdisWrapper</emphasis>: You can install
      Windows XP NDIS drivers for wireless cards with this item.
    </para>
  </listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Setting the system hostname</title>

<para>
A hostname is a unique name that identifies the system. This can be
any name that contains alphanumeric characters, for example:
<emphasis>linux.home</emphasis>. If you are going to use the system
as a server, you should use a fully qualified domain name (FQDN).
This is a name that consists of a hostname part, a domain name, and
a top-level domain. For example, <emphasis>mindbender.example.org</emphasis>
is a FQDN, in which <emphasis>mindbender</emphasis> is the hostname,
<emphasis>example</emphasis> is the domain name, and <emphasis>org</emphasis>
is the top-level domain.
</para>

<para>
You can change the current hostname of a machine with the
<emphasis>Set hostname</emphasis> item in the <emphasis>Network
&amp; Internet</emphasis> page in adminmenu.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-network-hostname-item">
<title>The <emphasis>Set hostname</emphasis> item</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/hostname-item.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
After clicking on the <emphasis>Set hostname</emphasis> item, a dialog with
the current hostname will appear (<xref
linkend="adminmenu-network-hostname" />. You can change the hostname
in the input field, and save the change by clicking on the <emphasis>Set
Hostname</emphasis> button.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-network-hostname">
<title>Setting a hostname</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/hostname.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Configuring network interfaces</title>

<para>
Various kinds of network interfaces can be configured through the
<emphasis>Network Configuration</emphasis> item that is available
on the <emphasis>Network &amp; Internet</emphasis> page in Adminmenu
(<xref linkend="adminmenu-networkconfig-item" />).
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-networkconfig-item">
<title>The <emphasis>Network configuration</emphasis> item</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/networkconfig-item.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
After launching the network configuration item a list of detected
network interfaces will be shown. The type of network interface
is shown as an icon. These icons are listed below, for left to right
the icons represent Ethernet/PPPoE, Wireless and PPP interfaces.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-networkconfig-ificons">
<title>Network interface type icons</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/networkconfig-ificons.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject> 
</figure>

<para>
You can configure an interface by selecting the interface, and
clicking the <emphasis>Add connection for selected card</emphasis>
button. Interfaces connection settings can be edited by selecting
the connection (the line below an interface entry), and clicking
on the <emphasis>Edit connection properties</emphasis> button. A
connection can be removed with the <emphasis>Remove connection</emphasis>
button.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-networkconfig">
<title>Overview of interfaces</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/networkconfig.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject> 
</figure>

<para>
When you add a connection, Adminmenu will ask you what kind of connection
you would like to set up <xref linkend="adminmenu-networkconfig-add" />. The
next sections describe the various connection types.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-networkconfig-add">
<title>Setting the connection type for a new connection</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/networkconfig-add.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>



<sect2>
<title>Setting up an Ethernet connection</title>

<para>
Ethernet networks are the most common form of wired local area networks
(LANs). If you choose to set up an ethernet connection, a dialog with
various tabs will appear (<xref linkend="adminmenu-networkconfig-ethernet" />).
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-networkconfig-ethernet">
<title>Configuring an Ethernet connection</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/networkconfig-ethernet.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The most important tab is the <emphasis>Network</emphasis> tab. This tab
is used to assign an IP address to the interface, and for setting up
various other parameters, like the gateway address. There two are ways of
setting the IP address and related information, namely <emphasis>Dynamic
assignment (DHCP)</emphasis> and <emphasis>Static assignment</emphasis>.
You should use dynamic assignment if there is a DHCP server on the network,
DHCP is a protocol for offering clients relevant IP information. If you
use DHCP, you can just select <emphasis>Dynamic assignment (DHCP)</emphasis>
from the <emphasis>IP Assignent</emphasis> pull-down button. This should
automatically configure the necessary settings. In some cases it is also
necessary to send a hostname to the DHCP server; you can do this by
marking the <emphasis>Send Hostname</emphasis> check-box, and filling in
the hostname.
</para>

<para>
If you choose to manually assign an IP address, there are various settings
that you have to fill in:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>IP Address</emphasis>: This is the address of the interface,
if you have a dedicated IP address, you can fill it in. If you are
on a private network (e.g. a home network), you can just pick an address
from a reserved private range, for example 192.168.1.x (replace
<emphasis>x</emphasis> with a number that is in the 1-254 range).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Netmask</emphasis>: The netmask is a network-specific mask,
if you use a private address range, and only change the last digit
(e.g. 192.168.1.x) you can fill in <emphasis>255.255.255.0</emphasis>.
Otherwise you should use the netmask that applies to the address range
that the address is in.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Broadcast</emphasis>: This is the address which is used
for broadcasts. For example, a broadcast address of 192.168.1.255
means that broadcasts are send to all hosts in the 192.168.1.x
range. You can usually use the default broadcast address that
Adminmenu suggests.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Default gateway:</emphasis> If there is a gateway on the
network that connects to the Internet, you should also enter the
address of this gateway if you want to be able to connect to the
Internet.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
If you do not know whether your network uses statis or dynamic assignments,
or what the settings for static assignments are, consult your network
administrator. The DNS tab is described in <xref linkend="netconfig-dns" />.
</para>

</sect2>

</sect1>

<sect1 id="netconfig-dns">
<title>Configuring DNS</title>

<para>
DNS servers have a very special task in networking. They translate hostnames
(for instance www.libranet.com) to IP addresses. To be able to use hostnames
the system needs access to one or more DNS servers. Almost all Internet
service providers provide DNS servers. DNS can be configured per interface
via the <emphasis>Network configuration</emphasis> item in Adminmenu.
To change the DNS server for an interface, select the network connection,
and click on <emphasis>Edit connection properties</emphasis>. The DNS
settings are then available under the <emphasis>DNS</emphasis> tab
(<xref linkend="adminmenu-dns" />). You can add a DNS server with the
<emphasis>Add</emphasis> button, or remove the selected server with the
<emphasis>Delete</emphasis> button.
</para>

<figure id="adminmenu-dns">
<title>Configuring DNS</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/adminmenu/network/ethernet-dns.jpg" format="JPG" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Manual configuration</title>

<para>
This chapter explains how some common network-related configuration files
work. Most things can be configured with adminmenu, but more experienced
users might prefer configuring things by editing the relevant configuration
files.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Configuring nameservers</title>

<para>
The name resolver is configured using the <filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>
file. This file is dynamically generated, based on the interface settings.
You manually add entries by editing
<filename>/etc/resolvconf/resolv.conf.d/base</filename> Nameservers that should be used can be configured by adding a lines of
the following form: <emphasis>nameserver &lt;IP address&gt;</emphasis>. For
example:
</para>

<screen>
nameserver 192.168.1.200
nameserver 192.168.1.201
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Local hosts</title>

<para>
Besides resolving using name servers specified in 
<filename>/etc/resolv.conf</filename>, GNU/Linux can also resolve hosts
that are specified in <filename>/etc/hosts</filename>. This file
is handy for adding names to local hosts, without the hassle of
configuring a local name server. Hosts are specified in the following
form: <emphasis>&lt;IP address&gt; &lt;name1&gt; ... &lt;namen&gt;</emphasis>.
This is an example of the <filename>/etc/hosts</filename> file:
</para>

<screen>
127.0.0.1       localhost localhost.localdomain
192.168.1.1     host1.example.net
192.168.1.2	host2.example.net
</screen>

<para>
Be sure that there is an entry for the host name that is used (you can
display the host name with the <command>hostname</command> command). If the
host name is not resolvable some programs refuse to work correctly.
</para>

<note>
<para>
If you want to use the same <filename>hosts</filename> file on a relatively
large number of machines, it might we worth looking at the
<emphasis>dnsmasq</emphasis> package. Dnsmasq can provide a
<filename>hosts</filename> file on one host to a complete network through its 
DNS server.
</para>
</note>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
