<!-- $Id: openoffice.xml,v 1.3 2004/08/06 07:44:05 danieldk Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="openoffice.html"?>
<title>The OpenOffice suite</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
This chapter gives a short introduction to the OpenOffice office suite
(officially named OpenOffice.org). OpenOffice is a fairly complete replacement
for other office suites, like Microsoft Office. It offers the most commonly
used functionality, an can open most major word processing, presentation
and spreadsheet formats. OpenOffice features the following functionality:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Writer</emphasis>: Word processor
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Calc</emphasis>: Spreadsheet
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Impress</emphasis>: Presentation software
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Draw</emphasis>: Vector-based drawing program
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>OpenOffice Writer</title>

<sect2>
<title>The Writer interface</title>

<figure id="openoffice-writer">
<title>The OpenOffice writer</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/openoffice-writer.png" format="PNG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
As you can see in <xref linkend="openoffice-writer" />, the OpenOffice Writer
actually looks a lot like other word processors. So, migrating to OpenOffice
should not be too difficult for most users. Let's start to have a look at
some GUI elements:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Working area</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
The working area is where most of the action will take place. As you can
see, the working area shows the paper you are virtually typing on, and
the thin grey lines mark the border of the area you can add text to. When
you type the text will be inserted at the point the blinking cursor was
at, and the cursor will be moved forward as you type text, indicating the
current typing position. You can also add other elements, such as images,
to the working area. You probably have noticed that the working area
is truly WYSIWYG (What You See Is What You Get).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Format bar</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
The format bar is used to change the appearance of your text, or parts of
your texts. There are multiple buttons and other elements that you can select,
you can see the meaning of each element by placing the mouse pointer on a
specific element. After a short time a tip will show, with a description
of the element. If you have no text selected the appearance will change
for the text that you will type after making the change. You can also change
the appearance of text that has already been typed, by selecting the text,
and making the necessary changes. You will see that the text will be altered
directly. Be aware that you can alway undo changes by using the &lt;Ctrl&gt;
+ &lt;z&gt; keys, or selecting the <emphasis>Edit -> Undo</emphasis>
menu item.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Page zoom</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
The page zoom indicator shows the zooming percentage of the document you
are currently using. If you have trouble reading smaller fonts, you can zoom
in to be able to read these fonts more comfortably. You can also zoom out
to get a better overview of a page or multiple pages. Select the
<emphasis>View -> Zoom...</emphasis> menu item to change the zooming 
percentage. There are also three special options, most notably 
<emphasis>Optimal</emphasis>, which will zoom to an ideal percentage for
editing. 
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Page style</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
Each page can have a page style. Page styles define options for a page, such
as page size and margins. Page styles can be changed through the
<emphasis>Format -> Page</emphasis> menu item.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Creating PDF files</title>

<para>
The PDF format is currently a very popular format for sharing documents
for printing or viewing. Since version 1.1 has integrated support for
creating PDF files. To make a PDF of the document you are currently
editing, select the <emphasis>File -> Export as PDF</emphasis> menu
option. This will open a file dialog, select the directory you would
like to safe the PDF to, and enter the filename of the document that
should be created (e.g. <filename>document.pdf</filename>). Finally,
press the <emphasis>Export...</emphasis> button. Another dialog will
appear that allows you to refine some options, and the range of pages
you would like to save to the PDF file. Select <emphasis>Export</emphasis>
to create the PDF file.
</para>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>OpenOffice Calc</title>

<sect2>
<title>The Calc interface</title>

<figure id="openoffice-calc">
<title>OpenOffice Calc</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/openoffice-calc.png" format="PNG" scale="60"/>
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
OpenOffice Calc is the OpenOffice spreadsheet. 
<xref linkend="openoffice-calc" /> shows what Calc looks like after launching
it. These are the basic interface elements:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Working area</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
The working area is divided in columns (vertical), and rows (horizontal).
Columns are referenced by letters of the alphabet (A, B, C, ...), rows
are referenced by number (1, 2, 3, ...). You can reference to a particular
cell by the column letter and row number, like A1 or C3. The contents of
a cell can be changed by selecting the cell and starting to type a number
or word.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Format bar</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
The formatting and appearance of information in cells can be changed. You 
can, for example change the appearance of a font or align the contents
in a cell another way. You can get a description of each icon on the format
bar by slowly moving the mouse over each icon.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Formula bar</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
You can see the contents or formula of a selected cell in the formula bar.
This bar can also be used to alter the contents of a cell.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Sheets</emphasis>
</para>
<para>
You can have multiple sheets open at one time, the sheet tabs helps you
to switch quickly between sheets. The arrow keys can be used to browse
available sheets. 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</chapter>