<!-- $Id: printing.xml,v 1.2 2004/05/09 14:48:06 danieldk Exp $ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="printer.html"?>
<title>Printer configuration</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
GNU/Linux supports a large share of the available USB, parallel and
network printers. Libranet GNU/Linux provides the CUPS printing system. 
CUPS can be configured via adminmenu, as well as the CUPS web interface. 
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Adminmenu configuration</title>

<para>
Adminmenu provides a special <quote>Printer</quote> section. This section
contains three buttons for configuring a printer. The <quote>Edit printer
configuration</quote> provides a graphical printer configuration tool.
<quote>Edit printer configuration (web interface)</quote> launches
a browser, and will allow you to configure the CUPS printing system
through the CUPS web configuration tool. Finally, the <emphasis>Turboprint
setup</emphasis> item provides the Turboprint configuration tool. Turboprint
is a commercial printing solution that provides advanced support for
many printers.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Printer configuration</title>

<para>
The <emphasis>Printer configuration</quote> item in Adminmenu provides
a comfortable tool for configuring printers using CUPS. After launching
this item a window showing printers that are configured pops up
(<xref linkend="printers"/>).
</para>

<figure id="printers">
<title>Configured printers</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/printer-printers.jpg" format="JPG" scale="50" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
A new printer can be added by double-clicking the <quote>New Printer</quote>
icon. This launches the printer configuration dialog (<xref
linkend="printer-welcome"/>, which allows you to select whether you would
like to configure a local printer or a network printer. In this section
we are going to look at how you can configure a local printer attached to
the computer.
</para>

<figure id="printer-welcome">
<title>Selecting the kind of printer you would like to add</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/printer-welcome.jpg" format="JPG" scale="50" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
After specifying that you would like to setup a local printer, the dialog
asks you to select which printer you would like to configure 
(<xref linkend="printer-select"/>). If you have
an USB printer that is turned on you can select it from the detected
printers list. If the printer is not shown you can manually select the
printer port manually. If you do not have an USB printer you should
select <quote>parallel port #1</quote> most of the times.
</para>

<figure id="printer-select">
<title>Selecting the printer you would like to configure</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/printer-select.jpg" format="JPG" scale="50" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The next step is to specify the manufacturer and model of the printer
(<xref linkend="printer-details"/>). If your printer is not yet supported,
it is a good idea to upgrade your Libranet installation using the
Libranet safe archive. There is a good chance that newer drivers for
CUPS support your printer.
</para>

<figure id="printer-details">
<title>Configuring the printer manufacturer and model</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/printer-details.jpg" format="JPG" scale="50" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The next thing the printer needs is a name(<xref linkend="printer-name"/>). 
The name and a description
for the printer can be configured during the next step. The name of
the printer is shown in many programs in the printer selection dialog.
A description for the printer is only optional.
</para>

<figure id="printer-name">
<title>Setting the printer name</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/printer-name.jpg" format="JPG" scale="50" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>

<para>
The final step will ask you for a confirmation 
(<xref linkend="printer-finish"/>). After confirming the settings the
printer should show up in printers window.
</para>

<figure id="printer-finish">
<title>Finishing the printer configuration</title>
<mediaobject>
<imageobject>
<imagedata fileref="../images/printer-finish.jpg" format="JPG" scale="50" />
</imageobject>
</mediaobject>
</figure>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Printer configuration (web interface)</title>

<para>
CUPS can be configured via a web interface. The configuration interface
can be accessed through the <emphasis>Printer configuration (web
interface)</emphasis> item in Adminmenu, or by visiting the following
URL in a web browser:
<ulink url="http://localhost:631/">http://localhost:631/</ulink>.
Some parts of the web interface require that you authenticate yourself.
If an authentication window pops up you can enter <quote>root</quote>
as the user name, and fill in the root account password.
</para>

<para>
A printer can be added to the CUPS configuration by clicking on
<quote>Administrate</quote>, and clicking on the <quote>Add Printer</quote>
button after that. The web interface will ask for three options:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Name</emphasis> - the name of the printer. Use a simple
name, for example <quote>epson</quote>.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Location</emphasis> - the physical location of the printer.
This setting is not crucial, but handy for larger organizations.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis>Description</emphasis> - a description of the printer,
for example <quote>Epson Stylus Color C42UX</quote>.
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist> 

<para>
You can proceed by clicking the <quote>Continue</quote> button. On
the next page you can configure how the printer is connected. If you
have an USB printer which is turned on, the web interface will show
the name of the printer next to the USB port that is used. After
configuring the printer port you can select the printer brand and
model. After that the printer configuration is finished, and the
printer will be added to the CUPS configuration.
</para>

<para>
An overview of the configured printers can be found on the
<quote>Printers</quote> page. On this page you can also do some
printer operations. For example, <quote>Print Test Page</quote>
can be used to check the printer configuration by printing a test
page.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
