<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="vim.html"?>
<title>Vim</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Vi was the first full-screen editor to be available for UNIX systems.
These days it is still the editor that is installed by default on
almost all UNIX(-like) operating systems. It uses very little
resources, and it is very fast, even on older computers and slow
network connections.
</para>

<para>
Vi may seem to be a bit obscure at first, but we advise you to learn
vi if you seriously want to learn the Unix and Linux basics.
Vi is very powerful, with  almost unlimited features.
You can use vi as an file editor by learning a few basic
commands. Sooner or later, you may find yourself addicted to vi. 
</para>

<para>
Libranet uses <ulink url="http://www.vim.org/">vim</ulink>, an extended version
of vi written by Bram Molenaar, as the default vi editor.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>The basics</title>

<para>
Vi is used in two modes: command mode, and edit mode. The command
mode is used to enter commands for, e.g. saving a file or searching
a phrase. The edit mode is used for actually typing text.
When vi starts, it is running in command mode.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Starting vi</title>

<para>
You can start vi from the console using the <command>vi</command> command:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>vi</command>
</screen>

<para>
or to use vi to edit an existing, or new file:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>vi filename</command>
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Inserting text</title>

<para>
To begin inserting text in the command mode, press the &lt;i&gt; key, for 
insert. Once you have pressed &lt;i&gt; you will see the cursor change and 
you will see <emphasis>--INSERT--</emphasis> in the lower left corner of the 
screen. This means that vi has switched to the edit mode. You now can start 
inserting and/or editing text.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Saving (writing) changes</title>

<para>
To save changes you made to a file, you need to be in command mode.  To
leave edit mode and enter command mode, you press the &lt;Esc&gt; key. The
cursor will change again, indicating that you have now switched to
command mode.  You can write (save changes) to the file that you were
working on with:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:w</command>
</screen>

<para>
or to save the changes to a file with a certain file name:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:w filename</command>
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Quitting vi</title>

<para>
To quit vi, you need to be in command mode. To leave edit mode and
enter command mode, you press the &lt;Esc&gt; key. The cursor will change
again, indicating that you have now switched to command mode. You can quit vi
with:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:q</command>
</screen>

<para>
or You can quit without saving any changes with:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:q!</command>
</screen>

<para>
It is also possible to combine some commands, for instance saving the
file and quitting vi. The following combined command will do this:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:wq</command>
</screen>

</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Help</title>

<para>
To get help when running vi, press the &lt;Esc&gt; key to enter command mode 
and then type:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:help</command>
</screen>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Searching and replacing</title>

<sect2>
<title>Searching a phrase</title>

<para>
You can search a certain phrase in a file using the search (/) command.
Just add the phrase you want to look for after the <quote>/</quote>:
</para>

<screen>
/cookies
</screen>

<para>
In this example vi will display the first instance it can find of
<emphasis>cookies</emphasis>, starting from the position the cursor
was at when the search was started.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Replacing phrases</title>

<para>
Phrases can be replaced one at a time with the following command:
<command>:s/old/new/</command>. For example, to replace the first
instance of <emphasis>cookies</emphasis> with <emphasis>cake</emphasis>
starting from the cursor position, enter the command mode, and
execute the following command:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:s/cookies/cake/</command>
</screen>

<para>
It is also possible to replace all instances, starting from the current
cursor position by adding a <quote>g</quote>:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:s/cookies/cake/g</command>
</screen>

</sect2>

</sect1>

</chapter>
