<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="vim.html"?>
<title>Vim</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Vi is the first full screen editor for computers. Vi is the standard
editor that is installed by default on any UNIX system. Because it uses
very little resources, it is very fast even on old computers and slow
network connections.  Vi is very powerful, with  almost unlimited
features.  You can use vi as an file editor by learning a few basic
commands. Sooner or later, you may find yourself editing a file with vi.
</para>

<para>
Libranet uses <ulink url="http://www.vim.org/">vim</ulink>, an extended version
of vi, as the default vi editor.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>The basics</title>

<para>
Vi runs in two modes: command mode, and insert (edit) mode.
When vi starts, it is running in command mode.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Starting vi</title>

<para>
You can start vi from the console using the <command>vi</command> command:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>vi</command>
</screen>

<para>
or to use vi to edit an existing file:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>vi filename</command>
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Inserting text</title>

<para>
To begin inserting text in the command mode, press the &lt;i&gt; key, for 
insert. Once you have pressed &lt;i&gt; you will see the cursor change and 
you will see <emphasis>--INSERT--</emphasis> in the lower left corner of the 
screen. You now can start inserting text.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Saving (writing) changes</title>

<para>
To save changes you made to a file, you need to be in command mode.  To
leave insert mode and enter command mode, you press the &lt;Esc&gt; key. The
cursor will change again, indicating that you have now switched to
command mode.  You can write (save changes) to the file that you were
working on with:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:w</command>
</screen>

<para>
or to save the changes to a file name:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:w filename</command>
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Quitting vi</title>

<para>
To quit vi, you need to be in command mode. To leave insert mode and
enter command mode, you press the &lt;Esc&gt; key. The cursor will change
again, indicating that you have now switched to command mode. You can quit vi
with:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:q</command>
</screen>

<para>
or You can quit without saving any changes with:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:q!</command>
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Help</title>

<para>
To get when running vi, press the &lt;Esc&gt; key to enter command mode and
then:
</para>

<screen>
<command>:help</command>
</screen>
</sect2>
</sect1>
</chapter>
