<!-- $Id: winonlin.xml,v 1.2 2004/09/08 20:46:30 danieldk Exp $ -->

<appendix> <?dbhtml filename="winonlin.html"?>
<title>Running Windows programs on Libranet</title>

<sect1>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
For a few years there are a few solutions for running Windows on Linux 
or running Linux programs under Linux. This article article describes 
some of these solutions, and how well they run with Libranet GNU/Linux.
</para>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>CrossOver Office</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
CrossOver Office is a product based on Wine, which allows one to run
some widely used Windows applications. It started as a product for
running Microsoft Office under Linux, but nowadays it supports other
applications as well. At the moment of writing supported applications
include most Microsoft Office programs, Adobe Photoshop, Quicken and
Lotus Notes. The CodeWeavers site has an application database with
support ratings for many applications (gold, silver, etc.).  </para>

<para>
A demo of CrossOver Office 4.2 is included in Libranet 3.0, and
is available through the <emphasis>Commercial software</emphasis>
page in Adminmenu.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Facts</title>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Reviewed version:</emphasis> 4.2</para>
</listitem> <listitem> <para> <emphasis
role="bold">Website:</emphasis> <ulink
url="http://www.codeweavers.com/" /> </para> </listitem>
</itemizedlist> </sect2> </sect1>

<sect1>
<title>VMWare</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
VMWare is a virtual machine, this means it emulates a PC on which
different operating systems can be installed. Hardware access to the
virtual machine is translated to instructions for the real
machine. The  disadvantage of this approach is that it is slower than
normal hardware  access, especially disk access is much slower. And be
aware that the  hardware is emulated, so you are bound by the
limitations of the  emulated hardware. Besides that VMWare is probably
to expensive for most  home users.  </para>

<para>
The big advantage of this approach is that one can run multiple
operating systems, even simultaneously. Officially supported guest
operating systems include Windows 95/98/ME/2000/XP, Novel Netware,
FreeBSD and Linux.  </para> </sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Facts</title>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Reviewed version:</emphasis> 4.0.5  </para>
</listitem> <listitem> <para> <emphasis
role="bold">Website:</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.vmware.com/" />
</para> </listitem> </itemizedlist> </sect2> </sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Serenity Virtual Station</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Serenity Virtual Station (or SVista in short) is a virtual machine,
much  like VMWare, that is currently being beta-tested. It targets a
wider  selection of host operating systems, at the moment Linux,
FreeBSD, OS/2  and Windows. Besides that it is less expensive than
VMWare (the  guestimated retail price for one platform is $99, and
$199 for all  platforms). The good support for OS/2 guests makes it a
good migration  tool for OS/2 users.  </para> </sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Facts</title>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Reviewed version:</emphasis> open beta 3 </para>
</listitem> <listitem> <para> <emphasis
role="bold">Website:</emphasis> <ulink
url="http://www.serenityvirtual.com/" /> </para> </listitem>
</itemizedlist> </sect2> </sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Win4Lin</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Win4Lin is a special piece of software that allows you to run Windows
95/98/ME on Linux. Unlike VMWare it is not a virtual machine. It
provides a special DOS environment in which Windows runs. At first
Windows is loaded from CD-ROM to the hard disk, after that Windows can
be installed per user. Win4Lin provides special hardware to Windows,
which communicates with the Linux kernel. The Windows files are
installed in the Linux filesystem (in contrast to most virtual
machines,  which use a hard disk image). This results in a very fast
way to run  Windows on GNU/Linux. On modern systems Windows boots in
about five  seconds. Windows can be used in a Window on in X or
full-screen (with  the <command>fwin</command> command). The fwin
launches X with a Windows as a full screen  program.
</para>

<para>
The biggest disadvantage is that Win4Lin requires kernel patches. These 
can be applied to the vanilla Libranet Linux kernel and requires a 
kernel recompile (which shouldn't be a problem for most users, thanks to 
AdminMenu). People who do a lot of gaming might be disappointed by the 
lack of Direct3D and OpenGL support (DirectDraw is partly supported). 
But overall it is a very good and fast solution to be able to run a 
large share of Windows programs.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Facts</title>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Reviewed version:</emphasis> 5.1
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Website:</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.netraverse.com/" />
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Wine</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Wine is free software that will run Windows 95/98/ME programs on Linux. 
Wine's name is a recursive acronym: "Wine Is Not an Emulator": Wine does 
not emulate the Intel x86 processor.  The goal of Wine is a full 
re-implementation of the Windows API which will make Windows unnecessary.   
Wine does not require Microsoft Windows, as it is a completely 
alternative implementation consisting of 100% Microsoft-free code, but 
it can optionally use native system DLLs if they are available. Well 
written windows programs will run as fast or faster in wine than they 
will in their native OS. 
</para>

<para>
There are many wine packages:
libwine (library) libwine-alsa (ALSA Sound Module) libwine-arts (aRts 
Sound Module) libwine-capi(ISDN Module) libwine-dev (Development files) 
libwinejack (JACK Sound Module) libwine-nas (NAS Sound Module) 
libwine-print (Printing Module) libwine-twain (Scanner Module) wine 
(Binary Emulator) wine-doc (Documentation) wine-utils (Utilities) 
winesetuptk (Configuration and Setup Tool).
At a minimum, you will need wine and libwine.  Winesetuptk is recomended 
for easier configuration.
</para>

<para>
The biggest disadvantages to using wine is having to do more work 
installing seperate configuration packages and it may not have as many 
recent APIs as some of the commercial programs.  The big advantage is 
cost and custom configuration.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Facts</title>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Reviewed version:</emphasis> 0.0.20040505-1
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Website:</emphasis> <ulink url="http://winehq.org/" />
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Cedega</title>

<sect2>
<title>Introduction</title>

<para>
Cedega is a commercial version of WINE from Transgaming that implement 
parts of the DirectX API. This makes it possible to run a selection of 
Windows(tm) games on GNU/Linux. A slightly impaired version of Cedega is 
available through the Transgaming CVS tree, this version misses some 
crucial code to run some Windows games. Cedega is offered a 
subscription, during the subscription period a subscriber can download 
the latest version of Cedega, and subscribers can vote which games have 
the highest priority to be supported in future versions.
</para>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Facts</title>

<itemizedlist spacing="compact">
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Reviewed version:</emphasis> 3.1
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
<emphasis role="bold">Website:</emphasis> <ulink url="http://www.transgaming.com/" />
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>
</sect2>
</sect1>

</appendix>
