<!-- $Id$ -->

<chapter> <?dbhtml filename="x11.html"?>
<title>X11</title>

<sect1>
<title>X Configuration</title>

<para>
The X11 configuration is stored in <filename>/etc/X11/xorg.conf</filename>.
X11 can be configured by hand by editing the
<filename>xorg.conf</filename> file. Fortunately Libranet provides some
useful tools to configure X11.
</para>

<sect2>
<title>Libranet Adminmenu</title>

<para>
Adminmenu provides an excellent X configuration tool. This tool can be
started by executing <command>adminmenu</command> in a shell. Select
"Configure X-windows", and "Configure X-windows" once more in the next
screen. This will launch the X configuration tool. The first thing that
will be asked is whether you want to set up X11 automatically or
manually. Detecting hardware automatically works perfectly most of the
time.
</para>

<sect3>
<title>Automatic detection</title>

<para>
After selecting "auto" the X configuration tool will try to detect
the display hardware, and will show the results afterward. If this is
not correct, select "No", this will start the manual configuration.
</para>
</sect3>

<sect3>
<title>Manual configuration</title>

<para>
Select <quote>manual</quote> to start the manual configuration of X. The 
configuration tool will start by asking which video driver should be used.
Right of the name of the driver the vendor and/or chipset series are
displayed. Select the driver that is appropriate. The next screen will
ask you how much video memory the card has. Normally you can leave this
blank and just press &lt;Enter&gt;. This will bring you to the mouse type
screen, select the mouse type you have, press &lt;Enter&gt;, and select
the mouse protocol that should be used. The next screen asks you what kind
of monitor you have. It is a good idea to have a look at the manual of
your monitor to find out what specifications your screen has. Selecting
a refresh rate that is too high can damage the monitor. Then select the
resolution you want to use. The resolutions you can use are dependent
on your monitor and video card. After that you can set the number of dots
per inch (DPI) for your monitor. Font sizes will be adjusted to the
DPI value to make fonts readable. The easiest way to set the DPI is
to select <quote>Set monitor DPI based on monitor size</quote>, which
allows you to set the DPI by the size of your monitor. Finally you can
set the color depth that should be used.
</para>
</sect3>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Automatical configuration</title>

<para>
The X11 server provides an option to automatically generate a
configuration file. X11 will load all available driver modules,
and will try to detect the hardware, and generate a configuration
file. Execute the following command to generate a X11 configuration
file: 
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>Xorg -configure</command>
</screen>

<para>
If X does not output any errors, the generated configuration can be
copied to the <filename>/etc/X11</filename> directory. And X can be
started to test the configuration:
</para>

<screen>
$ <command>cp /root/xorg.conf /etc/X11/</command>
$ <command>startx</command>
</screen>
</sect2>

<sect2>
<title>Interactive configuration</title>

<para>
X11 provides two tools for configuring X interactively,
<command>xorgcfg</command> and <command>xorgconfig</command>.
<command>xorgcfg</command> tries to detect the video card automatically,
and starts an tool which can be used to tune the configuration.
Sometimes <command>xorgcfg</command> switches to a video mode which
is not supported by the monitor. In that case <command>xorgcfg</command>
can also be used in text-mode, by starting it with
<command>xorgcfg -textmode</command>.
</para>  

<para>
<command>xorgconfig</command> differs from the tools described above,
it does not detect hardware and will ask detailed questions about
your hardware. If you only have little experience configuring X11
it is a good idea to avoid <command>xorgconfig</command>.
</para> 
</sect2>
</sect1>

<sect1>
<title>Window manager</title>

<para>
The "look and feel" of X11 is managed by a so-called window manager.
Libranet GNU/Linux provides many window managers. The following window
managers are widely used:
</para>

<itemizedlist>
<listitem>
<para>
WindowMaker: A relatively light window manager, which is part of the GNUStep
project.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
BlackBlox: Light window manager, BlackBox has no dependencies except the
X11 libraries.
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
KDE: A complete desktop environment, including browser, e-mail program
and an office suite (KOffice).
</para>
</listitem>
<listitem>
<para>
GNOME: Like KDE a complete desktop environment. 
</para>
</listitem>
</itemizedlist>

<para>
If you are used to a desktop environment, using KDE or GNOME is a logical
choice. But it is a good idea to try some of the lighter
window managers. They are faster, and consumer less memory, besides that
most KDE and GNOME applications are perfectly usable under other window
managers.
</para>

</sect1>

</chapter>
